Guide to the Hugh Rechnitzer Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Hugh Rechnitzer papers
1889-1906
MS 1142
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(2 boxes)
Chiefly photographs of China, ca. 1900-1905, some made during the Boxer Rebellion of 1900. Also photographs of Indonesia, Japan, Java, Singapore, and Vietnam where Rechnitzer traveled on business.There is also a small amount of family correspondence, personal photographs, and memorabilia.
Rechnitzer, Hugh, 1850-1906
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert Mahler in 1979.
Scope and Contents
Hugh Rechnitzer was an Austrian chemist who emigrated to New York in 1899. In 1900 he went to Shanghai as a member of the import-export firm of Charles Stürmann and traveled under the firm's auspices to Java in 1901, returning to Shanghai in 1902. He died on July 2, 1906 following an operation in Shanghai.*
The major part of the collection is made up of 510 photographs (ca. 1900-1905) taken by Hugh Rechnitzer while on business in China, Indonesia, Japan, Java, Singapore and Vietnam. Aside from a small number of personal photographs showing Rechnitzer with friends and associates on business and pleasure trips, and an interesting group documenting daily life in China, the bulk of the pictures record scenes of the Boxer Rebellion of 1900, showing the deployment and action of the foreign troops which ultimately suppressed the rebellion. The nations whose forces are shown in the photographs are France, Germany, Great Britain, India, Italy, Russia and the United States. Of particular interest are the photographs showing troops in action, such as the German navy bombing the Chinese fort at Taku in the Gulf of Chihli, or Chinese troops with the beheaded bodies of their enemies.
Rechnitzer was able to enter Peking, previously barred to foreigners, after a combined international force took the city and the Chinese court fled on August 14, 1900. His forty-eight snapshots of Peking show famous landmarks such as the Summer Palace and the Great Pagoda, European military forces in the city and street scenes.
* Sources: D. Paul Amara (Y.1981) "Library given collection of Boxer Rebellion photos," Yale Weekly Bulletin and Calender, Sept. 1-8, 1980, p.2, and the Papers.
The photographs are arranged alphabetically by place and are further identified by Rechnitzer's annotations on the verso in English or German. A small amount of family and business correspondence, bills and memorabilia complete the collection.
In 1979, Robert Mahler of New York City, a great-nephew of Hugh Rechnitzer, donated the photographs and papers to the Yale University Library.
Biographical / Historical
Hugh Rechnitzer: Austrian chemist who emigrated to New York in 1899; in 1900 went to Shanghai for the export-import firm of Charles Stürmann, and also travelled to Java.
Americans -- China; Asia; China -- History -- Boxer Rebellion, 1899-1901; Indonesia; Japan; Java (Indonesia); Singapore; Vietnam; Photoprints; Rechnitzer, Hugh, 1850-1906
- Inventory, 1889-1906, undated; 11" (2 boxes)
  - Photographs, (ca.1900-1905)
    - Batavia (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Canada (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - China
      - Buildings, temples, unidentified (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Harbor, river scenes (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Industry - Gun factory of Chan Chi Teng (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Military scenes - Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Persons, unidentified (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Street scenes (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Railroad scenes (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Views, unidentified (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Work scenes (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Chinese troops (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - U.S. troops (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - German troops (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - French troops (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Indian troops (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Italian troops (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Russian troops (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Chefoo (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Chiangkiang, Chiangwan (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Foochow (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Hankow (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Hangyang (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Hoang-ho (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Hong Kong (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Hsiling (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Hupee (Province) (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Kinkiang (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Nanking (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Ngankin, Pei-tai-ho (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Peitang (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Peking (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Shanghai (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Taku (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Tientsin (Box 1, Folder 35)
        General
        See also: box 1, folder 14
      - Tong Ku (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Woosung, Wuhu (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Yangtse River, Yangsten (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Yellow River (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Indonesia - Bogor (Buitensorg) (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Japan (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Java - Semarang (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - New York (City) (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Singapore (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Vietnam - Saigon (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Rechnitzer and friends on a trip. Views of buildings etc. Not otherwise identified (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Rechnitzer friends (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Personal Papers
    - Death notices, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Memorabilia, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Passport, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Bills, 1900-1904 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1889-1902 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Postcards, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)